Aldous Huxley Papers, 1916-1963
University of Houston Libraries
Aldous Huxley Papers
1916-1963
Huxley, Aldous, 1894-1963
1964-001
Born to a prominent British family in 1894, Aldous Huxley's career as a writer began in the 1920s with a sequence of novels and short story collections which lampooned the pretensions of post-World War I society. Interested in a variety of literary forms, Huxley also published books of essays, travel observations, and poetry. His works include Brave New World, Point Counter Point, The Doors of Perception, as well as short stories, essays, plays, literary criticism and Hollywood screenplays. This collection contains signed letters and manuscripts written by Aldous Huxley.
2 boxes, 52 items
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Biographical Note
Aldous Huxley was born in 1894 to a British family whose forebears included outspoken Darwin advocate Thomas Henry Huxley, his grandfather, and poet Matthew Arnold, his great-uncle. Huxley's career as a writer began in the 1920s with a sequence of novels and short story collections which lampooned the pretensions of post-World War I society. Interested in a variety of literary forms, Huxley also published books of essays, travel observations, and poetry. In 1928, he published the novel Point Counter Point, an ambitious work with a vast cast of characters which explored multiple points of view and the multiple aspects of experience.
In 1932, Huxley released the book which would become his most famous, Brave New World. In this cautionary tale of the future, babies are bred in test tubes to become workers who, as adults, are kept docile through games, “sleep teaching,” and the calming drug “soma.” The book's success brought him celebrity and fortune, but the novels which followed suffered from Huxley's inclusion of his own instructive rhetoric. Still as prolific as ever, he continued to churn out additional stories, essays, plays, literary criticism and, following his 1937 move to Southern California, several Hollywood screenplays.
In the final ten years of his life, Huxley experimented with LSD, writing about his experiences with the hallucinogen in his book The Doors of Perception. He died in 1963.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains signed letters and manuscripts written by Aldous Huxley between 1916 and 1963. The bulk of the letters were sent to Huxley's friend Robert Nichols, an English poet and dramatist, between 1916 and 1935. The manuscripts included are for the novel Antic Hay, the essay “America and the Future,” the book Arabia Infelix and Other Poems, and the poem “Fifth Philosopher's Song, From Leda.” The manuscripts for “America and the Future” and Arabia Infelix show Huxley's corrections to his work.
The collection is arranged in two boxes, one of manuscripts and one of correspondence. The items are arranged chronologically within each box.
Much of Aldous Huxley's personal collection of manuscripts, diaries, and papers were destroyed when his Los Angeles home burned in 1960, enhancing the significance of this collection. Special Collections also houses a large number of Huxley's books, including many first editions and autographed copies.
Index Terms
Terms are either Library of Congress Subject Headings or taken from local sources.
Subjects (Persons)
Huxley, Aldous, 1894-1963
Subjects
Authors, English -- 20th century
Formats
Correspondence; Typescript drafts
Acquisition
These items were purchased by the University of Houston Libraries from C. Dorman David in September 1964. Items 22 and 23, Box 2, (two 1945 letters) were donated in memory of Mrs. Ethel Romansky.
Access Restrictions
Open for research.
Detailed Description
- Manuscripts
  - Antic Hay. Typescript. [1923]. Inscribed and signed 1962., 344 pp.
  - Chapter One, title page and pp. 1-16. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chapter Two, pp. 17-34. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chapter Three, pp. 35-52. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chapter Four, pp. 53-69. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chapter Five, pp. 70-90. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chapter Six, pp. 91-107. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chapter Seven, pp. 108-115. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chapter Eight, pp. 116-122. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chapter Nine, pp. 123-148 (two p. 134s). (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Chapter Ten, pp. [149]-166. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Chapter Eleven, dividing page and pp. 167-182. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Chapter Twelve, pp. 183-196. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Chapter Thirteen, pp. 198-207 (no page 197). (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Chapter Fourteen, pp. 208-222. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Chapter Fifteen, pp. 223-227. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Chapter Sixteen, pp. [228-248]. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Chapter Seventeen, pp. [249-259]. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Chapter Eighteen, pp. [260-283]. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Chapter Nineteen, pp. [284-292]. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Chapter Twenty, pp. [293-302]. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Chapter Twenty-One, pp. [303-335]. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Chapter Twenty-Two, pp. [336-343]. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - America and the Future. Typescript, corrected. [ca. 1927-28]., 19 pp. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Arabia Infelix and Other Poems. Typescript, corrected. Nine poems from the book. [ca. 1929]., 15 pp. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Fifth Philosopher's Song, From Leda. Typescript, inscribed. undated, 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Correspondence
  - [ca. 1916 July 12]. To Robert Nichols., 3 pp. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1918 Mar. 16. To Robert Nichols., 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1923 May 13. To Robert Nichols., 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1923 July 2. To Robert Nichols., 2 pp. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1924 Oct. 5. To Robert Nichols., 2 pp. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1925 Apr. 10. To Robert Nichols., 2 pp. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1925 June 14. To Robert Nichols., 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1926 Feb. 3. To Robert Nichols., 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 1926 Nov. 14. To Robert Nichols., 2 pp. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 1927 Jan. 18. To Robert Nichols., 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 1928 Mar. 17. To Mr. Rimington., 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 1928 May 23. To Robert Nichols., 3 pp. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 1928 Oct. 10. To Robert Nichols., 2 pp. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 1928 Oct. 20. To Mr. Rimington., 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 1929 Aug. 2. To Robert Nichols. 1 p. With photograph. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - 1929 Dec. 14. To Robert Nichols., 2 pp. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - 1930 Feb. 17. To Robert Nichols., 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - [1930 May 4]. To Robert Nichols., 2 pp. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - [1930 Oct. 18]. To Robert Nichols. With drawing., 2 pp. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - 1931 Sept. 15. To [G. Wilson] Knight., 4 pp. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - 1935 Jan. 13. To Robert Nichols. 3 pp. With envelope. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - 1935 Sept. 20. To Robert Nichols., 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - 1945 Jan. 30. To Anne Wachtel. TLS. 1 p. With envelope. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - 1945 Mar. 2. To Anne Wachtel., 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - undated To Robert Nichols., 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - undated To Robert Nichols., 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - [1963 March 4]. To Mrs. Pope. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Miscellaneous clippings. (3) (Box 2, Folder 28)